The death domain cleric is one of the
most powerful subasses in Balders's Gate
3 thanks to incredibly powerful necrotic
spells and abilities. With her most
powerful spells locked away out of
sight, most players have no idea how
broken the death cleric really is. But
after you see what this build can do,
you'll never touch life or light again.
With powerful necromancy spells like
circle of death, dethrone, blight,
vampiric touch, inflict wounds, and so
many more, the death domain cleric is
unmatched in their ability to unleash
massive necrotic damage. Pair that with
their feature, inescapable destruction,
which makes your attacks ignore
resistance to necrotic damage, and the
death domain cleric becomes unstoppable.
And that's not all. Reaper, when paired
with a droid caster, makes your cantrips
hit every single target within a large
AoE. And if all that wasn't enough, the
death cleric has a secret interaction
that changes everything, which we'll go
over in the leveling section. To get
started, choose death domain at level
one. You'll gain reaper, which causes
your necromancy cantrips that only
target one creature to target an
additional creature. For your race, this
build is perfect for any type of elf.
Wood elf would be ideal for the
increased move speed, but any elf is
good because we want fay ancestry so
that we cannot be magically put to
sleep. This will come in handy later
when we use glyph of warding sleep on
top of ourselves when we're surrounded
by enemies to put them all to sleep
without falling asleep to it ourselves.
Shadow heart is a half- elf, so she
works perfectly for this build, too.
This is what you'll want for ability
points. We want primarily wisdom and
constitution. Wisdom will be important
since it improves our spell casting, and
intelligence is our spell-casting
ability modifier for when we multiclass
into necromancy. So, you'll want that to
be high as well. You can completely dump
strength and charisma since I wouldn't
recommend the death domain cleric as the
face of your party. For your spells,
you'll want to choose guiding bolt,
command, bless, and inflict wounds.
Guiding bolt grants advantage on the
next attack roll against the target
creature and deals 2d6 radiant damage.
This is your ranged singlet target
damage spell. Inflict wounds is also
great for single target, but requires
melee range and deals 3d10 necrotic
damage. Since inflict wounds is an
attack roll and melee range, you can
guarantee it's a critical hit by using
it on targets that are sleeping or
paralyzed from hold person. Bless is
always great for improving your team's
ability to land attacks, and command is
solid crowd control. You can also disarm
enemies with command drop weapon. At
level two, you'll gain your first
channel divinity charge. This can be
used to turn undead, which causes undead
creatures to flee in a large area of
effect. This will get much stronger at
level five once we gain destroy undead.
We also gain Touch of Death. This allows
you when hitting a creature with a melee
attack to use a channel divinity charge
to deal extra necrotic damage. The extra
necrotic damage is 5 + 2 multiplied by
your cleric level. This will trigger
when you use inflict wounds. And if your
attack would otherwise kill the target,
it won't activate, which is great. At
max level, your inflict wounds when
paired with touch of death can deal
around 100 necrotic damage at max level
or twin spell it for 200 damage. Then at
level three, we gain access to a bunch
of very good spells. From our domain, we
gain blindness and ray of infeeblement.
Blindness is a unique crowdcontrol spell
because it can disable an enemy without
requiring concentration. Ray of
Infeblement causes attacks that use
strength to deal only half damage. This
means strong melee attackers are perfect
targets for this spell to make them
easier to manage. We also gain access to
aid, warding bond, spiritual weapon, and
hold person. Aid and warding bond are a
must for any party, so make sure to use
them. And hold person is a great spell
to guarantee critical hits for your
inflict wounds and other party members
attacks. Spiritual weapon can be a
source of bleed days or gaping wounds.
When paired with Bual's benediction, you
can give your whole party advantage with
a spiritual weapon. Not only that, but
if you ever need to apply threatened to
a target, you can do so quickly and
easily with a spiritual weapon placed
right next to them. This can allow your
rogue to get sneak attacks as needed. At
level four, you'll unlock another can
trip. I like to choose resistance to
help with saving throws during dialogue.
When it comes to prepared spells, there
are a number of good choices depending
on what you need, such as lesser
restoration just in case you need to get
rid of any powerful negative conditions,
silence to stop a powerful spellcaster,
or even calm emotions. Calm Emotions is
a really underrated level two
enchantment spell that has a ton of uses
besides using it to protect your party
from the harpy's charm or to snap
Kazador's servants out of their charm.
Calm Emotions can actually be used in a
number of boss fights or other difficult
encounters to make them much easier.
Within act one, you can use calm
emotions to remove the red cap's blood
lust, which lets them attack three times
and regain 2d8 hit points if it lands a
killing blow. It can remove owl bear's
rage, which grants the owl bear in the
cave the multi-attack ability, two
strength and constitution, as well as 12
temporary hit points and resistance to
all physical damage. It can also remove
null's frenzied fury, which grants them
three attacks per turn. And then there's
the spider queen's wrath used by the
phase spider matriarch on tactician
difficulty and above which can be
removed by using calm emotions. The
spider queen's wrath causes the phase
spider matriarch to gain four strength,
lose one AC, but also gain an additional
attack per turn and gain resistance to
all damage. And that's just some of the
more powerful enrage conditions that
calm emotions can remove in act one. One
of the more notable uses for calm
emotions is actually on Orin. If you
cause her to lose her mind by telling
her that Saraveak betrayed her by
telling her own mother to kill her, she
will gain a condition called a
missedmost scarlet as a side effect of
ball forcibly transforming her into the
slayer. Calm emotions can remove this
condition that grants Orin 25 temporary
hit points and a plus two bonus to
strength and advantage on wisdom saving
throws. For your feet, you'll want to
get war caster. This amazing feat grants
advantage on saving throws to maintain
concentration on a spell. We'll want
this for when we get spirit guardians at
level five. Since we'll be in close
range dealing damage, we'll likely be
getting hit and we don't want to lose
concentration on spirit guardians.
You'll also gain the ability to use
shock and grasp as a reaction when
enemies leave melee range, which they
tend to do to escape spirit guardians.
This shocking grasp benefits from your
wisdom modifier, so it's also much
better than if you'd get the cantrip.
Shocking grasp makes your target unable
to take reactions and it has advantage
against creatures with metal armor. At
level five, you'll get a massive power
spike. Death clerics automatically learn
animate dead and vampiric touch. Animate
dead zombies attack applies a condition
called crawling gnaw. If an enemy is
killed while having this condition, a
newborn zombie is automatically spawned
from their corpse. The newborn zombie
also applies this very same condition,
allowing you to potentially raise an
army of zombies. Each turn, the newborn
zombies take one necrotic damage and
only have 10 HP, so they will all
eventually fade away. Our other spell,
vampiric touch, deals 3d6 necrotic
damage and heals you for half as many
hit points. This can be a great way to
sustain your death cleric in melee
combat against a small number of
enemies. Against many enemies, you're
better off using spirit guardians, a new
thirdle spell you unlock this level.
Spirit guardians is one of the staples
of this build. When cast, nearby enemies
take 3d8 radiance or necrotic damage per
turn, and their movement speed is hald.
When casting it, you can select the
variant that deals necrotic damage or
radiant. And since we haven't unlocked
inescapable destruction yet, which makes
our attacks ignore necrotic resistance.
Choose whichever variation makes sense
for the enemy you're fighting. Spirit
guardians will be the primary spell we
concentrate on and is the main reason we
chose warcaster at level four. At level
five, you'll also gain access to glyph
of warding. This spell is ideal for
causing area of effect sleep. Attacks
made in melee range against the sleeping
target will automatically be critical
hits. And crowd control in general is
very powerful. If you're surrounded by
enemies, you can cast this directly on
yourself. And because we're an elf, we
are immune to sleep thanks to fay and
cestry. At level five, your cantrips
also gain an additional damage die. Toll
the dead now deals 2d12 necrotic damage.
Bursting sineu now deals 2d10 and bone
chill now does 2d8. And since you can
target two enemies with each cantrip
thanks to Reaper, this is essentially
like adding two additional damage dice.
At level five, you also gain an
incredibly powerful passive feature
called destroy undead. Whenever you
successfully turn an undead creature, it
also takes 4d6 radiant damage. This can
deal a huge amount of radiant damage if
you're surrounded by a lot of undead.
However, there is another source of
turning undead that you'll want for this
build. Gandrel's Inspiration is an
uncommon heavy crossbow which grants
sacred munitions. Infuse your crossbow
bolts with holy energy. For the rest of
your turn, your ranged attacks inflict
turned against undead. This hidden
weapon action is perfect for our cleric.
Use sacred munitions right before
shooting an arrow of many targets, which
causes your ranged attack to ricochet to
nearby targets, including targets that
are invisible or protected by sanctuary.
Every single undead hit by your arrow of
many targets will become turned and take
4d6 radiant damage. Absolutely amazing.
And what's great about sacred munitions
is that it has a 100% chance to turn
undead because there is no saving throw
to resist it. You'll find Gandel's
inspiration on Gandel right outside
Auntie Ethel's Narlled Tea House in act
one. You also don't need to be
proficient with heavy crossbows to use
sacred munitions. At level six, we will
gain inescapable destruction. This
passive feature makes spells you cast
ignore resistance to necrotic damage.
We'll now favor using the necrotic
version of spirit guardians unless our
target is completely immune to necrotic
damage. We also gain a second channel
divinity charge allowing for more uses
of touch of death or turn undead. I like
to prepare silence since it can also be
useful in so many situations. At level
seven, you gain two additional spells
from your domain that are always
prepared. Blight and death ward. Blight
is a powerful singlet target spell which
deals 8d8 necrotic damage and always
deals the maximum amount of damage when
cast on a plant and they also have
disadvantage on the saving throw against
it. In act two, the shadowcursed
shambling mound and other vine bllights
are all considered plants and as such
they will take the maximum damage from
blight since they have necrotic
resistance. As a death domain cleric, we
will still deal maximum damage, ignoring
their necrotic resistance, making death
domain clerics the most capable class in
the entire game for taking on these
enemies. Blight also has a hidden
interaction. It can target any creature
affected by sanctuary. This makes it a
great choice to prepare when going up
against Carnis the Dryer. Our other
domain spell, death ward, is always
great. When death ward is applied, the
next time damage would reduce the
affected entity to zero hit points, it
remains conscious with one hit point
left. The spell must remain prepared or
the condition is lost. In our case, as a
domain spell, it is always prepared,
which is great. It's also great for
honor mode. When facing Orin's edict of
ball, instead of instantly dying, death
ward will activate and keep you alive.
At level seven cleric, we can now also
prepare banishment. This causes you to
temporarily banish your target to
another plane of existence. This control
spell has some really nice utility. In
act three, if a Steel Watcher is
self-destructing, you can banish it and
the explosion will be nullified. This
can potentially save your party from a
lot of damage since the Steel Watcher
will immobilize your party through its
linear area of effect maim ability and
then self-destruct right on top of you.
The same idea can be used against Anser
right before his gathering power ability
will go off. Instead of running for
cover, you can just cast banishment.
Then at level eight, cleric, we gain
divine strike necrotic. Once per turn,
deal 1d8 necrotic damage in addition to
your weapon's damage when you make a
melee or ranged attack. We can take
advantage of this by using our bonus
action to make a ranged attack. This is
possible through hand crossbows or
through the fabricated arbolasts bonus
action ranged attack. We also gain our
second feat and this time choose dual
wielder. This will give you the ability
to wield two of the strongest staves in
the entire game, the staff of cherished
necromancy and marcoish gear. We'll talk
more about the power of these staves in
the equipment section. Also, while dual
wielding two melee weapons, you gain
plus one AC. For your new spells to
prepare, choose calm emotions or remove
curse depending on what you're up
against. From here, we're going to begin
multiclassing. At level 9, take your
first level into wizard. For your can
trips, choose mage hand, minor illusion,
and firebolt. These are entirely for
utility purposes. Mage Hand can throw
items at enemies or grab items out of
reach for you. Minor illusion can be
used to group up enemies before a fight,
and firebolt can ignite any smoke powder
or explosives as needed. For your
spells, choose shield, long strider,
magic missiles, feather fall, enhanced
leap, and disguise self. You won't be
able to prepare all of these, so switch
them out as needed. Shield takes
priority as it's the only real spell we
need since the others should come from
another party member already. At level
10, take your second level into wizard
and choose the necromancy subclass. This
grants us two important feats. First, we
gain necromancy savant. This halves the
cost to learn necromancy spells from
scrolls. Learning these spells will only
cost 25 gold per spell level. We also
gain grim harvest. Once per turn, if you
kill a creature with a spell, you regain
hit points equal to twice the spell slot
level used, thrice if it's a necromancy
spell. This means we regain 15 hit
points if we slay a creature using a
necromancy spell that costs a level five
spell slot, such as dethrone. Dethrone
is one of two spells that we are going
to need to transcribe into our wizard
spell book. A scroll of dethrone can
only be found in one place deep within
the vaults of sorcerer sundries behind
the Carus door. The Carus section can be
unlocked by opening doors in this order.
First silver hand, then abjuration, and
then silver. Pulling the lever at the
end and returning to the beginning of
the door puzzle lets us enter the Carus
door. Alternatively, you can just use
knock on the Carus door. Once inside,
read the annals of Carus and you'll
receive a scroll of dethrone. And you
can also loot the scroll of dethrone,
which is sitting right next to the book
for a total of two. Learn it to gain the
ability to cast it repeatedly. You also
want to learn Circle of Death. The
scroll of Circle of Death can only be
found in three places within act three.
one in a buried chest in Rivington
inside a barn. Actually, the same barn
where you can find the strange ax if it
survived. You can also find it in the
basement of Phil Graves mansion. And the
third location in an opulent chest in
the cloister of somber embrace. When I
checked these three locations, Phil
Graves basement was the only place of
the three where I found the scroll. So,
be prepared to check all three
locations. Once you have the scroll,
learn it to be able to cast it
repeatedly. You'll also want to learn
Misti step. This build wouldn't get it
otherwise, so make sure to learn it from
a scroll when you can. At level 11, take
your first level into sorcerer. For your
subclass, choose draconic bloodline.
This brings our base AC to 13 while not
wearing armor, which we don't plan to,
and we also gain one hit point per
sorcerer level. For your spells, make
sure to choose shield. We're going to
unprepare the wizard version of shield
to make space for new powerful [music]
spells that we learned from the scrolls.
At level 12, get your second level in
sorcerer and pick up metamagic twin
dispel. This will allow us to twin
[music] cast spells like dethrone,
inflict wounds, blight, banish, hold
person, and many more. You can also
choose extended spell if you want to
double the duration of vampiric touch,
spiritual weapon, banish, or other
spells and cantrips. And next up are the
best pieces of equipment for our death
domain cleric. Now, the idea behind
these equipment choices is that we are
going to be maximizing our spell save DC
and attack rolls while also dealing
massive amounts of necrotic damage and
healing ourselves in the process. So,
the best helm for our death cleric is
the hood of the weave. This helmet
grants a plus two bonus to spell save DC
and spell attack rolls and can be
purchased from mystic kerrion in
Philgrave's mansion in act three. The
best cloak for our death domain cleric
is the cloak of the weave. This cloak
grants a plus one bonus to spell save DC
and spell attack roles. And it also has
a passive feature called absorb
elements, but it's currently bugged and
doesn't work properly. You can purchase
this from Helsick in the devil's fee in
act three once her special stock is
unlocked. The best armor for our death
cleric is the robe of the weave. This
armor grants a plus one bonus to spell
save DC and spell attack rolls. Also,
whenever the wearer succeeds a saving
throw against a spell, they regain 1d6
hit points. The robe of the weave can be
obtained within Ramisith's tower inside
a globe of invulnerability. You'll need
to see invisibility to see a lever,
which requires a DC20 arcana check to
disable the globe. Be careful because if
you fail the check, a trap will trigger.
The best gloves for our death cleric are
the hell dusk gloves. These gloves grant
you a plus one bonus to spell attack
rolls and spell save DC and also grant
you the rays of fire cantrip. This
canrip hurls three rays of fire, each
dealing 3d6 fire damage. They also add
1d6 fire damage to your weapon attacks,
but you mainly just want these for the
spell save DC and attack rolls bonus.
The best boots for our death cleric are
the hell dusk boots. These boots give
you the ability to teleport to an area
and deal 2d6 fire damage where you land.
This is great to help us spread spirit
guardians around to all of our enemies.
It also grants infernal evasion,
allowing you to use your reaction to
succeed a saving throw that you
otherwise would have failed. And you can
find these boots in a locked gilded
chest on the top floor of Worms Rock
Fortress. And the best amulet for our
death cleric is the amulet of the
devout. This amulet grants the wearer a
plus two bonus to spell save DC. It also
gives you an additional channel divinity
charge that is restored upon short rest,
not long rest as the item says. This
makes this pretty much the best amulet
for any cleric. This means we can use
touch of death or turn undead more often
per short rest. And you can get this
amulet from the main offering chest in
the basement of the Stormshore
Tabernacle. And the best ring for our
death cleric is the ring of fa wild
sparks. This ring says, "While your
sorceress tides of chaos feature is
active, you will always trigger wild
magic when casting spells." However,
what the ring doesn't say is that it
also increases your spell DC by one.
This is why we actually want this ring
for our death cleric, even though at
first glance it would appear useless for
us. And you can acquire this ring from
Auntie Ethel in the basement of the
Blushing Mermaid. The other ring for our
death cleric is the ring of mental
inhibition. This ring is great because
once an enemy fails a saving throw
against one of your spells or actions,
they gain mental fatigue for two turns.
This gives them a minus one penalty to
wisdom, intelligence, and charisma
saving throws for every turn remaining.
When there are five or more turns
remaining, the target takes 1d4 psychic
damage and is no longer mentally
fatigued. This is great synergy because
we'll be casting a lot of spells that
trigger a saving throw and increasing
our chances to succeed is always great.
And you can find the ring of mental
inhibition in a locked chest within the
house in deep shadows just east of the
shadowed battlefield waypoint. And the
best mainhand weapon for our death
cleric is the staff of cherished
necromancy. This weapon causes creatures
to have disadvantage on saving throws
against your necromancy spells. Perfect
for our death cleric. It also gives us
life essence harvest, which allows us to
cast any necromancy spell without
consuming a spell slot. Life essence is
gained when the wielder kills a hostile
creature and is consumed when we use a
spell to cast a necromancy spell without
using a spell slot. Now, previously it
was bugged and you could just cast
necromancy spells for free indefinitely,
but it is fixed and life essence is
perfect for a costly necromancy spell
like circle of death, eye bite, blight,
or even dethrone. The best offh hand for
our death cleric is Marco gear. This
staff grants a plus one bonus to spell
save DC and spell attack rolls. It also
grants arcane battery which allows you
to cast a spell without using a spell
slot. The staff also grants Caresca's
favor which can be used in a number of
different ways. I recommend choosing
bone shaking thunder. This gives you
access to destructive wave which you can
then choose the necrotic damage variant.
This deals 5d6 necrotic damage and
thunder damage. And since we have
inescapable destruction, our necrotic
damage will go through resistance. Even
better, since this spell is gained
through marish, it doesn't cost the
level five spell slot destructive wave
usually does. Bone shaking thunder also
grants us resistance to thunder damage
and our thunder spells deal additional
damage equal to our proficiency bonus.
Since there is no necrotic version of
Caresca's favor, this one is nice to
gain access to destructive wave. And the
best ranged weapon for our death cleric
is the fabricated arbolst. This ranged
weapon grants you a weapon action called
illuminating shot. For a bonus action,
you can fire a shimmering bolt that
inflicts one turn of radiating orb. This
allows us to get value from our bonus
action each turn and get value from
divine strike necrotic which activates
from this ranged attack adding 1d8
necrotic damage. And that's the build.
Hopefully that's the best death cleric
build you've ever seen. And if so,
please give it a like and subscribe as
it helps me out a ton. Thanks and I'll
see you in the next